Guide to the Ship Scalers, Dry Dock, and Boat Yard Workers Union, Local 541 (Seattle, Washington) Records
Special Collections, University of Washington Libraries
The 1980s marked the total decline and fall of the Ship Scalers Union. In 1980, another reform candidacy was attempted when Bob Barnes, a younger, white member of the union, convinced Hearde to run again. Together they ran for the respective positions of secretary treasurer and business agent on a platform of reform, arguing it was poor accounting to have the positions combined. These claims were not unfounded. A 1979 audit of the union’s financial records revealed $13,750.78 missing from Harrison’s books and union funds. Eventually the union was reimbursed for the missing funds by the corporation which bonded with Harrison and produced a check specifically noted “for loss caused by Van Harrison.” Together Heard and Barnes advocated for change in the union’s internal affairs by calling for more accountability. Again, their election was contested by the LIUNA-backed Harrison and began a six-year battle of court cases in which the SSU continued to seek more independence from LIUNA, which was having its own international officers indicted on racketeering charges in Washington D. C. The series of court cases brought the union into further financial despair, and paired with the economic troubles in Seattle industries in the 80s, directly contributed to the end of the union.
In 1980, the union listed a total of 837 members with roughly ninety percent of them working, but by 1986, The Seattle Post-Intelligencer noted that membership dropped by a third “to 550, with less than half working.” Waning membership and hard economic times caused the union to fall behind in payments to various creditors as well as LIUNA, who said that Local 541 stopped paying dues in 1984. Finally in May of 1986, LIUNA suspended Local 541 for “failing to pay $60,000 in affiliation fees and pension contributions” and for owing upwards of $135,000 to its creditors. In April, 1986, Oscar Hearde published the article, “An urgent appeal to Seattle Citizens for help” in The Facts, a Central District progressive newspaper. In it, Hearde attributed the union’s financial failures of the union specifically to the “Reagan Administration,” arguing that Reagan “failed to send enough work to the shipyards in the Northwest to supply the work necessary to keep our membership employed.” The appeal was to raise money to keep the SSU in Seattle, but ultimately the union was forced to sell its E. Madison headquarters to pay their debts and control of the union was subsequently transferred to Local 252 in Tacoma. Despite its lackluster finale, the Ship Scalers Union was dissolved amid controversy that existed since the union’s founding in the mid-1930s. In his appeal, Hearde wrote that the Ship Scalers Union possessed “a long history of being the most integrated, industrial Union of the Northwest,” and it is “one of the only Unions in the Northwest willing to stand up for the rights of our membership against what we consider to be the dictatorial powers of the International.”
Conclusion: Pablo O’Higgins Mural and Martin Luther King Jr. Way
Despite Local 541’s shortcomings in its later years as a financial institution, it managed to leave a lasting impression on the soul of Seattle’s civil rights movement and in the corpus of the city. According to Del Castle, the early years of the union were led by idealists and was among the first to “challenge housing discrimination and prompted the first lunch-counter ‘sit-ins’ in the city.” Beyond these policy and social changes though, there are two highly recognizable and visible physical remnants of the SSU’s impact in Seattle: A commissioned mural which still hangs in the city and the changing of a street name which runs through Seattle’s Central District.
1945 perhaps marked the highest union accomplishment in their involvement with the national dialogue. Mexican muralist Pablo O’Higgins agreed to paint a mural depicting the SSU’s history as a strongly anti-racist, anti-discriminatory, and progressive force in social politics. O’Higgins was in Seattle on the invitation of a University of Washington faculty member to give a visiting workshop on fresco painting at the university. Union officials who were familiar with his fresco work in Mexico approached him and asked him to do a mural for the auditorium of their Belltown union hall. According to O’Higgins, “It will portray the struggle against racial discrimination and the unity of international labor as one of the most important developments for future peace.” O’Higgins solicited opinions from members of the union about what should be included in the mural and “for three weeks before I even planned this mural… I went out to the shipyards and talked to the workers—got their ideas and suggestions as to what they would like.” Del Castle himself is portrayed in the mural in the lower right-hand corner, “whimsically” sporting a hammer and sickle on his lapel (see Figure 7).
The 58-foot, thirteen-panel mural marked the peak of the union’s involvement and its history in many ways parallels the history of the SSU. When the union was forced to move out of Belltown in 1959, the mural was donated to the University of Washington and lost until February of 1975, when it was discovered in an outdoor storage area on the university’s campus. After a series of ownership disputes that lasted until 1977, the mural was to be placed at the Chicano cultural center El Centro de la Raza in Beacon Hill. The transfer would be effected once El Centro could raise enough money to have the panels transported there and ensure preservation safety in their building. Until then, the mural was to hang in Kane Hall, the main auditorium building at the University of Washington. The agreement between the University of Washington and El Centro was that the UW would pay for restoration costs, and El Centro would pay for transportation and new fixtures for their building. It seems that El Centro did not raise enough money as the mural is still hanging today on the second floor of Kane Hall on the university’s campus. The mural itself depicts the SSU at its most active period of history and is representative of the SSU’s social involvement and publicity by containing, according to Clever, “all the clichés and idealized visions of the revolution that Castle and others had hoped would spread to American shores.” That the mural remains visible to the public today is a testament to the Ship Scalers Union early and militant social commitment.
The final bout of the Ship Scalers Union came in 1982 with the city-wide controversy over the change in name of Seattle’s Empire Way to Martin Luther King Jr. Way. The Ship Scalers Union was central to the organization boycotting Empire Way stores that opposed the name change and ultimately proved successful for signing the bill into law. In the summer of 1982, the Seattle City Council approved a motion to change the name of Empire Way, a major South End and Central District arterial. The vote was cast and the name change would be signed into law and take effect later that year. In between the council vote and signing it into law, many merchants on the eight-mile stretch of road formed the Empire Way Merchants’ Association in protest and lobbied the city not to change the name on the grounds of the financial burdens it would cause the stores to change their stationary and signs, and the city to change its street signs.
In direct response to the Association, many Central District residents formed the Coalition for Respect and began boycotting Association stores. The Ship Scalers Union acted as liaison of the Coalition, issuing press releases, flyers, and aiding in organizing boycotts. The contention over MLK Way was one of the most important local issues of the 80s, in part because it affected so many merchants, but primarily because of what it revealed about Seattle’s racial myopia. In fact, violence began at one boycott in early September, 1982 when patrons and the owner of the Empire Way Tavern began verbally harassing picketers. According to a Coalition press release in The Facts, “the tavern owner shouted racist insults, made other threatening and argumentative remarks, and pushed one African American woman. She then punched a white male picketer in the face, knocking off his glasses, and called him a ‘White nigger.’” While the rhetoric was more tempered by the Coalition, their charges were not insubstantial. In one SSU flyer, the union argued, “It really gets down to some people just not wanting a street in front of their place named after a Black man…. This attitude, which is at the root of the movement to block the name change, displays a total lack of sensitivity to the fact that much of the money these merchants take is from Blacks and others who Dr. King spoke for.” Eventually, the bill was signed into law and the street was renamed, though it is doubtful such a victory was possible without the aid of the Coalition for Respect and the Ship Scalers Union’s resurgent activism amid the city’s growing complacency regarding discrimination.
Through its periods of advocacy, the union seemed to maintain sight of its original values, preserving that rhetoric in all progressive stances it took. In the end, the union was unable to make a comeback from years of mismanagement and its disputes with LIUNA, but Local 541 of the Ship Scalers Union presented Seattle with a challenge to change its atrophied stance toward race relations during its effectual fifty-year history. Through its militancy and progressive voices, the SSU contributed to a lasting alteration of Seattle’s racial climate. The union’s activism signifies something beyond the gestalt of its members; it highlights the racial struggles Seattle and the nation underwent throughout the 20th century and causes a re-evaluated imagining of Seattle’s progressivism. Even though the Ship Scalers Union itself was neglected in its later years by its international, the SSU continued to subvert Seattle’s refusal to acknowledge its own minority residents.
Accession 4571-001 is arranged into nine series, some of which are divided into subseries based on intellectual content. Files within series and subseries are arranged chronologically or remain in their original order as appropriate.
Series I: Constitutions, Charters, Preambles, and By Laws, 1955-1986
Arranged chronologically.
Series II: Minutes, 1939-1986
Arranged into subseries based on creating officer or committee, then chronologically within those subseries. Subseries A contains regular membership meeting minutes, Subseries B contains international general executive board minutes, Subseries C contains local executive board meeting minutes, Subseries D contains combined executive board, regular membership meeting, and benevolent corporation meeting minutes, Subseries E contains membership, repair, and safety committee meeting minutes, Subseries F contains Seattle Metal Trades Council meeting minutes, and Subseries G contains Northwest Employees Retirement Fund meeting minutes.
Series III: Financial Records 1946-1988
Arranged into three subseries and arranged chronologically within those subseries. Subseries A contains internal financial records, Subseries B contains tax records, and Subseries C contains audit information.
Series IV: Correspondence 1939-1987
Arranged into subseries by creating body or topic, then arranged chronologically. Subseries A contains general correspondence, Subseries B contains local officer correspondence files, arranged by creating officer then chronologically, Subseries C contains correspondence regarding financial and contract negotiation administration, Subseries D contains correspondence with and regarding the Laborers International Union of North America, Subseries E contains correspondence regarding internal tensions within the union, and Subseries F contains correspondence regarding strikes.
Series V: Subject Files 1944-1987
Arranged into subseries according to topic, then chronologically within those subseries. Subseries A contains files on elections, Subseries B contains membership files, Subseries C contains files on community activism, Subseries D contains safety files, Subseries E contains files regarding organizing efforts against racial discrimination in the workplace and have special historical significance due to their age, Subseries F contains files on the Pablo O'Higgins Mural, Subseries G contains publications, Subseries H consists of Robert J. "Bob" Stanley files (a worker who died on the job), Subseries I consists of Cossie Burrus files (a worker who died on the job), Subseries J consists of Michael C. "Chris" Wells files (a worker and Olympic athlete who died on the job), and Subseries K consists of files on the strike at Northwest Tank Service.
Series VI: Legal Files 1943-1991
Arranged into subseries based on specific cases and topics, then arranged chronologically within those subseries. Subseries A contains general legal files, Subseries B consists of files on legal conflicts with the Laborers International Union of North America, Subseries C contains Oscar Hearde's legal files, Subseries D contains files on local trial board charges, Subseries E contains Van T. Harrison's legal files, Subseries F contains Yvonne Quiroga's legal files, Subseries G consists of member death records, Subseries H contains LaVerna Oliphant's legal files, Subseries I contains files detailing legal conflicts with employers, Subseries J consists of National Labor Relations Board files, Subseries K consists of files on arbitrations, Subseries L contains files on Equal Employment Opportunity and Human Rights Commission cases, Subseries M consists of Jesse L. Washington's legal files, Subseries N consists of Rex Ricardo, Jr.'s legal files, and Subseries O consists of Robert "Bob" Barnes' legal files.
Series VII: Member Files (Restricted) 1944-1986
Arranged into subseries based on the existing, loosely alphabetical arrangement already present in the collection. Names of members are not included in the online finding aid, but can be found on folder labels within the physical collection. Subseries A consists of non-alphabetized or multi-member files, Subseries B consists of member files from A to Z, and Subseries C contains files on employees of Local 541.
Series VIII: Employer Files 1967-1986
Arranged into subseries based on employer, then arranged chronologically within those subseries. Subseries A contains files on Todd Pacific Shipyards Corporation, Subseries B contains files on Foss Launch and Tug, Subseries C contains files on Northwest Enviroservice, Inc., Subseries D contains files on Northwest Tank Services, Subseries E contains files on Marine Power, Subseries F contains files on Lake Union Drydock Company, Subseries G contains files on Rowe Machine Works, Inc., Subseries H contains files on Northland Marine Lines, Inc., Subseries I contains files on Duwamish Shipyard, Inc., and Subseries J contains files on Lockheed Shipbuilding and Construction Company.
Series IX: Photographs and Posters 1942-1985
Arranged by format and chronologically.
Accession 4571-002 is arranged into nine series based on topic and format. Files within each series are arranged according to their original order within the collection.
Series I: Pablo O'Higgins Mural, 1975-1983
Series II: Robert A. Barnes Files, 1977-1988
Series III: Legal Subject Files, 1955-1987
Series IV: Constitutions, 1971
Series V: Meeting Minutes, 1968-1986
Series VI: Internal Tensions, 1951-1987
Series VII: Correspondence, 1951-1985
Series VIII: Strikes and Grievances, 1946-1986
Series IX: Elections Posters, 1982-1983
See descriptions of individual accessions below.
Open to all users, but access to portions of the papers is restricted. Contact UW Special Collections for details.
Carole A. Aaron, "The Second Annual Puget Sound Area Top 50 Report," Seattle Business 1980.
Marion Anderson, "The Impact of Military Spending on the Machinists Union, 1979.
Ed Barnes and Bob Windrem, "Six Ways to Take Over A Union,"Mother Jones August 1980 issue.
Dick Clever, "Shipyard Local Rebels Against International Office,"U.S News and World Report August 31, 1981.
Dick Clever, “Ship Scalers: A union’s half century of turmoil, tragedy and triumph,” The Seattle Times Pacific Magazine, May 2, 1982, 6-8.
Adam Farley, "The Ship Scalers Union and Seattle’s Racial Progressivism in the 20th Century," The Waterfront Workers History Project. Retrieved (February 11, 2014) from http://depts.washington.edu/dock/ship_scalers.shtml.
Oscar Hearde and Ester Hearde, "An Urgent Appeal to Seattle Citizens for Help,"The Facts April 30, 1986.
Robert M. Kaus, "Strike it Rich for Socialism!,"The Washington Monthly 1980.
Laborers' International Union of America, "Convention Proceedings," 1975.
Lee Moriwaki, "Fliers urge Boycott of Empire Way name-changing foes,"The Seattle Times August 19, 1982, B1.
The North American Congress on Latin America, "Report on the Americas: Crisis in Nicaragua", Volume XII No. 6, 1978.
Gigi Peterson, "Recobrando / Recovering The Struggle against Racial Discrimination: The Journey of the Pablo O’Higgins Mural for Seattle Ship Scalers Union," Labor: Studies in Working-Class History of the Americas, Volume 8, Issue 4 (2011) pp.7-40.
Michael Scott, "Labor at the Crossroads: 'Right-to-Work' Laws and the Future of American Trade Unionism," Manuscript.
"A.F.L. will not be in parade," The Seattle Times August 30, 1946, 8.
"Public Protest Rally (Paid Advertisement),"The Seattle Times October 19, 1949, 13.
"Attorney for Reds to Speak in Seattle,"The Seattle Times February 27, 1950, 10.
"Walkout at Lockheed,"The Seattle Times January 3, 1968, 52.
"Scalers Back to Work at Lockheed,"The Seattle Times January 9, 1968, 7.
"Scalers in Walkout at Lockheed,"The Seattle Times October 26, 1972, 47.
"Lockheed Shipscalers Stay off Job,"The Seattle Times October 27, 1972, 29.
"Some Lockheed Shipscalers Return to Work," The Seattle Times October 28, 1972, 26.
"Seattle Laborers Seek Injunction Against International's Interference,"Labor News October 27, 1981, 5.
"Union Suspends Ship Scaler's Local,"The Seattle Post-Intelligencer May 8, 1986.
"Mexican muralist honored at U.W.,"The Seattle Times Tempo October 24, 1975.
"Back In Sight,"The Seattle Times August 20, 1977, A7.
Dick Clever, "Founder to Speak,"The Seattle Times June 6, 1951, 5.
Adam Farley, "The Ship Scalers Union and Seattle's Racial Progressivism in the 20th Century,"The Waterfront Workers History Project University of Washington, HSTAA 498D Winter 2010. Copyright Adam Farley 2011.
George E. Flood papers, University of Washington Special Collections, Acc # 0911-001.
John Caughlan papers, University of Washington Special Collections, Acc # 0704-001.
Philip S. Foner, Organized Labor and the Black Worker 1619-1973 New York: Praeger Publishers, Inc., 1998, 165.
Dana Frank, "Race Relations and the Seattle Labor Movement," Pacific Northwest Quarterly 86, no. 1 (1995): 35-44.
Bruce Nelson, "The 'Lords of the Docks' Reconsidered: Race Relations among West Coast Longshoremen,"Waterfront Workers Urbana: University of Illinois Press, 1998, 165.
Pablo O'Higgins, "The Struggle Against Racial Discrimination." 1945. Kane Hall, University of Washington (Seattle).
Larry Richardson, "Civil Rights in Seattle: A Rhetorical Analysis of a Social Movement" (PhD diss.), Washington State University, 1975.
Quintard Taylor, "The Forging of a Black Community: Seattle's Central District from 1870 through the Civil Rights Era," The University of Washington Press 1994.
James G. Thompson, "Should I Sacrifice to life 'Half-American,'"Pittsburg Courier January 31, 1942, 3.
"De Lacy Assumes Ship-Scaler Duties,"The Seattle Times August 14, 1940, 4.
"Fair Practices Bill Rejected,"The Seattle Times March 19, 1946, 12.
"Gerhard Eisler's wife to speak here," The Seattle Times March 31, 1947, 14.
"Mrs. Fisher Barred from Moose Hall,"The Seattle Times April 1, 1947, 3.
"Eisler's Wife Gets Funds,"The Seattle Times April 3, 1947, 4.
"War Fund Asked at Lenin Rally,"The Seattle Times February 6, 1948, 4.
"CIO Council Convention to Open Tomorrow," The Seattle Times October 20, 1949, 51.
"Last Time Tonight: The Film of 1952," The Seattle Times March 13, 1952, 45.
"Labor Unions, Social Reform to be Topics," The Seattle Times November 6, 1964, 31.
"Antipoverty Board Off on 'One Wing,'" The Seattle Times November 16, 1964, 31.
"Lockheed Shipscalers Walk Off Job,"The Seattle Times August 25, 1966, 11.
"Scalers, Lockheed in Agreement,"The Seattle Times August 27, 1966, 7.
Barnes, Robert Alan; Cameron, Donald T.; Ship Scalers, Dry Dock, and Miscellaneous Boat Yard Workers Union, Local 541 (Seattle, Washington)$vArchives; Labor Archives of Washington (University of Washington); Seattle, Washington (State); Labor unions$zWashington (State)$zSeattle; Civil rights movements$zWashington(State)$zSeattle; African American labor union members; Labor unions and communism
Personal Papers/Corporate Records; Labor Unions; Labor History; Ships and Shipping; African Americans; Washington (State); Seattle
- Ship Scalers, Dry Dock, and Boat Yard Workers Union, Local 541 (Seattle, Washington) Records, 1939-1991; 4571-001; 16 cubic feet 16 boxes
  The Ship Scalers, Dry Dock, and Boat Yard Workers Union, Local 541 (Seattle, Washington) Records, Accession 4571-001, ranges in date from 1939 to 1991. The accession consists of records of the union during that time. Included are Constitutions, Charters, Pre-ambles, and Bylaws of the union; financial records including internal accounting, tax documents, and audit records; correspondence and contract negotiations; subject files on elections, membership issues, community activism, safety committees and efforts, the Pablo O'Higgins Mural, publications related to the union, workers Robert J. "Bob" Stanley, Cossie Burrus, and Michael C. "Chris" Wells, all of whom died on the job due to sub-par safety standards and efforts, and the strike at Northwest Tank Service; Discrimination files with special historical significance, documenting collective action taken against a racist and sexist supervisor by a group of largely African American women workers in 1944; legal files documenting internal legal struggles, along with litigation against the Laborers' International Union of North America and various employers; restricted member files and files on employees of the local; and employer files documenting working conditions and contract enforcement. Also included in the collection are photographs, posters, and elections materials.
  Case files of members in boxes 12-14 are to be used only by researchers who sign a statement agreeing not to disclose identities of members documented in such files.
  Donated by Bob Barnes, May 7, 1996.
  - Series I: Constitution, Charter, Preamble and By-Laws, 1955-1986 (Box-folder 1/1-1/17)
    - Local 541 Bylaws Committee, 1955-1981 (Box-folder 1/1)
    - Local 541 Bylaws Committee, 1955-1981 (Box-folder 1/2)
    - Articles of Incorporation of Seattle Shipscalers Benevolent Corporation, 1956-1956 (Box-folder 1/3)
    - Photocopy: Application for Charter to the International HOD Carriers', Building and Common Laborers' Union of America, AFL, 1956-1956 (Box-folder 1/4)
    - Seattle Shipscalers Benevolent Corporation: Articles of Incorporation and Bylaws, 1956-1956 (Box-folder 1/5)
    - Photocopy: Constitutions of the International Hod Carriers' Building and Common Laborers' Union of America: Local Unions, District Councils, Ritual, 1956-1956 (Box-folder 1/6)
    - 1973 Election Results and Seattle Shipscalers Benevolent Corporation: Bylaws, Resolutions, Installation of Officers Oath, 1956-1973 (Box-folder 1/7)